So this is how our history with shared
counters would work. We have the program
counter. We take some of the lowermost
bits. Use that to index into what we
will call PHT or pattern history table.
This is a table that simply keeps the
history bits alone for that branch. So
if we have an 11 bit history, this table
will have 11 bits per entry. So it
doesn't have the two bit counters. But
we do need the two bit counter to
eventually tell us whether the branch is
supposed to be taken or not taken. So
what we do is we take this history from
this table combine it in some way
usually using an exor with the bits of
the PC and use that to index into what
we still will call the branch history
table. This branch history table has
entries. Each of these entries is just a
single twobit counter. So each entry is
very small and that entry will tell us
whether we should be predicting taken or
not taken. When the branch outcome is
known, we use the same history and PC
combination to index back into this two
bit counter increment or decrement it
based on the current decision on a
branch and then we shift in that pattern
also into the PHT entry so that this
history is ready for the next prediction
on this particular branch. So the idea
is that the program counter here tells
us which branch we are talking about. We
hope that the pattern history table has
one history per branch that we have.
Different histories and different pieces
will result in different two-bit
counters being used and thus the
decisions will be made for kind of like
a combination of the history and the PC.
Note that it is possible for another PC
to map somewhere here. But that history
when exor with that PC gives us maybe
the same two bit counter. So it is
possible to have some overlap here. But
the idea is that this way for each PC we
have a single history of all the
possible histories where there is like
two to the nth of them. We're really
using only a very small number of
counters because very few histories are
actually happening. And that means that
if we have a relatively large array of
two- bit counters, the possibility of
conflict is very low. But this allows us
to have a lot of bits of history. For
example, if we take 11 bits of PC and we
index into the PhD with them, we will
need 2 to the 11th histories times let's
say 11 bits of history. We exert those
11 bits with these 11 bits. So we will
have 2 to the 11th two bit counters. So
the overall cost of this predictor will
be 2 to the 11th * 11 for the histories
plus 2 to the 11 * 2 for the counters
which ends up costing us 26 kilo bits.
This is much less than what the cost
would be if we had an array of two bit
counters for each possible history in
each entry over here. pretty much these
2 to the 11* 2 would need to be in each
entry here if we didn't do the ex
sorting like this. Note also that we
don't have to have these numbers here
and here equal. We can for example take
something like 10 bits of the PC to
index into the PHT which gives us only 2
to the 10th histories and have a 16 bit
history so that we can have two to the
16th entries here and so on. It still
will keep the overall cost in the you
know tens of kilobits not megabits or
gigabits that we would get if we try to
put together long histories with
dedicating two-bit counters for each
possible history in each entry.